Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Heat.
Well, hello. Welcome back to the Ask
Abijet show. Good evening and good day
to all of you wherever you are in the
world. It's great to see you all again.
Uh I'm going to take questions today
from the live chat from the super chat
and we're going to do as many as
possible but before that let's see who
all is there on the live chat. Let me
greet as many of you as I can quickly. I
can see Shri Ramachandra Namaha. I can
see Dya Ranganat. I can see Savia Sait
Aayush Singh. Uh, Spuri URI uh, Savaria
say it again. Aush Singh geopolitical
dub from Indor Dak Panipal from Kolkata.
Anandpai satellite suas
ready project smiling Buddha Lakshai
Hitan Shua from Gujarat welcome Shashank
Koshik welcome back. Sager Torat are you
singing again. Ram Shukla from Kpur.
Well good evening. HB Ashoto Kumar Ashu
Gautam Ashu Gautam Somia
Explorer 1 Kapalain Rashmi Ratur from
Rajasthan good evening Suhas ready from
Bangalore good evening Bangaluru Sumit
Rana Vidant Shukla Arindam Das Sager
Torat
uh Uju
who else daddy Tashi Beast Vamsi Khale
Vamshi Kalem Akash Ba Rashik Udin Suas
Reddi from Bangalore. Animeh Paul Anatab
Singh Gorish Kei from Dublin. Mlelan Ram
Ashoto Kumar Aush Yadav Vidant Shukla
Shashank again Sagert Turat Suran Brian
Stellar Opai Opai
uh who else do we have? Uh Karan Singh,
Ratur, Adimesh, Chat DSP, Shik Kazu,
Patrick the Keller, Alka Shikari,
Master Dis etc.
Uh U has missed two weeks but welcome
back sir Apernna Saha Shri Shri an
Shukla and everybody else. Okay. So I'm
going to take questions about
geopolitics today so that we are focused
on one topic. Let's do that. Right. So,
please get going. Let's let's see what
questions you all have. I'll answer as
many as I can and I will prioritize uh
super chats if there are any, but uh
we'll take as many as we can. All right.
So, Soldier Boy says we need to suffer.
We need to suffer for 20 years. Can you
please clarify what kind of pain? What
type of pain uh I was talking about? So
I was talking about the fact that you
know
uh
we know what's happening right now. Shri
Donald Trump is imposing sanctions or
not sanctions but tariffs on India 25%
tariffs which is going to make life
difficult for India from a economic
perspective trading perspective. Uh the
US is one of our major trading partners
and now our goods will be priced at
uncompetitive rates in the US. So it's
going to be not so good for our for our
economy and if you see my last episode
of geost strategy in that in that I have
shown how it's going to affect our GDP
roughly you know a rough ballpark
analysis of that and Trump is
threatening even more
tariffs punitive tariffs because we are
trading with Russia because we are
purchasing Russian oil and so on and the
US sees India as a long-term adversary
because India is growing India has
naturally been at the top of the totem
pole when it comes to the global
economies. India has always been the
largest economy historically for the
past 2,000 years. There's been a blip in
between some 300 years or so when we
were under European occupation, right?
When they destroyed our economy, but we
are rising again and they don't want us
to rise. So, they're going to do
everything they can. The Americans,
okay? And you have to understand that's
what any great power will do. Any great
power will ensure will try to ensure
that any rising power will be nipped in
the bud and it doesn't become a threat
long term. So, that's what they're going
to do. They're going to try their best
to clip our wings and ideally from their
perspective to turn India into a vasal
state. So it'll all depend on the
quality of India's leadership. Right now
we have good leadership. Well, let's see
how it goes going forward. So that's
what I'm talking about 20 years of pain.
If if we can somehow go through those 20
years without caving in, without
becoming a vasal, without engaging,
without getting drawn into a major
conflict somewhere, then we're going to
be a 15 20 trillion economy. We're going
to be a whole different beast and then
it's going to be very hard for anybody
to mess with us. So, it's a question of
about 20 years
and those 20 years will be tough. So,
that's what I mean by that. Okay. Rohan
Sunja says what will happen to Armenia
if Iran falls in war? Well, life will
get will yeah you to life will be
difficult for Armenia. So let's take a
look at the map to understand
uh what we are talking about here. Let's
see the map because the map gives us a
lot of information that otherwise we
won't understand. So we are talking
about a nation in the Caucasus region
which is Armenia. It's a landlocked
nation currently. uh it used to be a
much larger kingdom in the past.
All of Azarbaijan was once part of the
kingdom of Armenia but yeah this is
where we are today and you can see that
there's parts of Armenia that the
Azarbanis have taken over. See it's now
Azarbaan. Google officially recognizes
these regions as part of Azarbaijan. Now
it wasn't the case earlier. Uh so and
Armenia is a nation that uh has suffered
terribly at the hands of Turkey in the
past. Uh the Armenian genocide which
Turkey refuses to uh recognize as a fact
but it is a fact right? We know that
there are multiple waves of the Armenian
genocide starting in the last quarter of
the 19th century and the last major wave
of the Armenian genocide the the hammer
blow was around 1915 or so. You can look
up the history to see the exact details
and exact dates. Uh so Armenia has
suffered tremendously at the hands of
the Turks and Azarbaijan is a very
staunch Turkish ally. It's a Turk
culturally Turk nation. Okay. Um and the
two nations uh Turkey and Azarbaan would
like to wipe Armenia off of off the map
of the world. And Armenia well right now
it has a few allies. It's interesting
that you know Israel is aligned with
Turkey for its own geopolitical reasons
and against Armenia and Iran is
supporting Armenia. India is supporting
Armenia. Uh so you have a Hindu nation,
a Sunni, a Shia Islamic nation both
teaming up to support a Christian nation
Armenia. Uh it's very strange but it's
interesting. So if and and India is
supplying various kinds of weapon
systems to Armenia like the Paka
multiarrel uh multiarrel rocket system,
Swati radars and whatever else we
supplying to Armenia and we are
typically doing this by trans shipping
the weapons packages via Iran by road.
Okay. Now if Iran a staunch I mean one
of the major allies of Armenia were to
fall in the war Armenia will be in deep
deep deep trouble seriously deep trouble
and uh it may end up being wiped off the
map of the world so it's very important
for Armenia's perspective from Armenia's
perspective that Iran continues to
survive and it continues to exist and
does not fall in any war so I hope that
explains the situation right now we have
Zean gaming says who says now that Trump
and even the Indian opposition leader
has have said that India lost five jets
to the Pakistan air force are you
willing to admit that that's what
actually occurs
so if Trump says something I'm supposed
to admit because the white man said that
and somebody else said that somebody
else made an allegation do you have
evidence of this
are you willing to admit are you Indian
are you Pakistani what are you exactly
not Sorry.
Um, all right.
What next do we have?
Feminist Slayer, quite a name, says,
"Can green hydrogen, solar, and other
renewables make India self-sufficient in
terms of energy or is nuclear the
future? Are there other any other
alternatives to explore?" Okay. uh green
hydrogen it's it's hydrogen gas and
you're proc you're producing it via
green means which means non uh means
that are not dis not not harmful to the
environment that's what we mean by green
hydrogen it's produced in a sustainable
manner in in a way that doesn't harm the
environment that's green hydrogen so we
have green hydrogen which is hydrogen
gas which we will combust with oxygen to
produce by water vapor and energy that's
one uh solar energy which produces
electricity uh other renewables like u
like wind energy and geothermal energy
and hydroelect electric energy and so on
and so forth. These are renewables. Are
all of these renewables
sufficient to make India self-sufficient
in terms of energy or do we need to add
nuclear in the mix? I think nuclear is a
great option. It's a very clean form of
energy as long as we do it properly.
Right? We have had a few issues outside
outside of India. We've had Chernobbile.
We've had a 3mile island in the US which
was a nuclear accident. We've had
Fukushima in Japan as a consequence of
the 2011 disastrous earthquake. Uh and
maybe a smattering of other incidents.
But overall nuclear energy is extremely
safe as long as you know what you're
doing and you know how to handle it. So
I think nuclear energy I don't so
nuclear energy is another factor that we
can use. Are there other alternatives to
explore? Green alternatives. Well,
there's hydroelect electric, this
geothermal and wind energy.
Um, I suppose there could be some more.
There's there's waves, you know, waves,
tidal waves and all. Not just tidal
waves, but just regular waves in the sea
that you can use to uh the you can put
boys there and the up and down going of
the boy can be used to generate
electricity. There's a whole lot of
creative ways in which you can generate
electricity and energy. But those all of
those depend on the climate on the
weather on on capriccious factors that
are not under your control. Uh solar for
example only half of the time you will
get energy because at night time there's
no solar energy. Uh wind energy depends
on the winds. Uh geothermal depends on
whether bas factors. Uh so all of these
other forms of energy they depend on
factors that are not under our control.
U nuclear energy it's entirely under our
control. Um so I think nuclear energy
needs to be a major component of our
energy strategy uh going forward. Uh but
can the real question is can we entirely
do away with uh with fossil fuels, oil
and gas? That's the big question. Is it
even possible to do that? Let's say you
have to fight a war. Unfortunately, you
have fighter planes, right? Can you
power fighter planes with hydroelectric
energy? I mean, yep, with with the
lithium ion batteries, you can't. You
need fossil fuels for that. Uh so, I
think fossil fuels are still very much
an integral component of any nation's
energy. uh strategy long-term we'll see
how it goes. Uh so that's why I would
say that because of the capricious
uncertain nature of solar other
renewables etc. it's it's a better it's
always a good strate good uh strategy to
have something like uh something you can
control entirely like nuclear energy
even green hydrogen. Yep.
Okay. I am Koshik says okay this is not
geopolitics I'm so sorry but I've said
it very clearly it's geopolitics I
really appreciate the fact that you
asking me questions but today is not the
day for physics questions please
understand sir please today I I've put a
pinned comment saying that today is a
geopolitics live stream
okay so uh today the audience is here to
see geopolitics because that's what I've
announced so we will not let the
audience down and uh yeah so there we
Vunsoon says, "What will be the impact
of Trump's tariffs on the software
sector? Why are we not able to build
companies like AWS that could have
protected our data integrity? We could
have we could have led as Alibaba is the
only big player here from Asia. What's
going to be the impact of Trump's
tariffs?" It it depends. First of all,
right now he's announced 25% tariffs.
is also threatening more additional
punitive tariffs because we are trading
with Russia. There's this uh bill by
Lindsey Graham that that threatens 500%
tariffs
two nations that that are purchasing
Russian oil. So, it's all all going to
depend on how it goes. We are still
engaged in trade negotiations with the
Americans and Trump is very miffed for
for for a variety of reasons with India.
uh but but assuming it's going to stay
at 25%. I am look I have not done an
analysis of the software sector
particularly specifically that what's
going to be the impact on the software
se sector but overall it's going to have
an impact of about a a delterious
negative impact on the Indian GDP growth
over the next year which is about 0.2 to
0.4%
0.2 to 0.4% 4% ballpark rough figure I'm
giving you. So the RBI has forecast okay
that the Indian GDP will grow at about
6.5% let's say over the next year. So
the Trump tariffs will bring it down to
either 6.3 or 6.1%. which is not good
right that's what I can tell you I
haven't seen the impact of the software
sector for that I'll have to sit down
and do some number crunching and all
that I have to see what was the total
volume of uh trade software exports from
India to the US how much was the revenue
for India over the past year right and
assuming 25% hike and then what's the
effect I have to do some calculations I
don't know right now I've not done that
but you get the point you get the point
right so if you are charging for example
if I am a software company, you know,
old-fashioned uh labor arbitrage
software company, and I'm hiring uh pro
Indian programmers at at at pitious
salaries and I'm billing the client,
American clients, $20 an hour, let's
say, okay, for the work they are doing,
my my software employees are doing. So,
if it's $20 an hour, then with 25% hike
on that, what's 25% of $20? It's $5,
right? 1/4 $5. So now it's going to
you're going to it's going to cost about
25. You can do that sort of calculation.
Maybe that's not the right way to do it,
but you you get the point. So it's going
to be u you know it's going to be
tougher for India. That's the kind of uh
effect it's going to have. Why aren't we
able to build companies like AWS? I
think it's a question kind of question I
took yesterday. It's because Indian uh
all these Indian corporations don't have
the appetite for risk. They don't want
to innovate.
They don't want to innovate. They're
getting money the oldfashioned way by do
by engaging in labor arbitrage. They
just they're just happy with it. They
have no desire to innovate. It's it's so
sad to see this. The kind of people who
are running these corporations.
Absolutely. We've had so many gigantic
Indian software companies the past
several decades, right? All working for
American clients. How many software
products, new software products have the
Indian companies created? How many
Facebooks, how many LinkedIn, how many
Twitters, how many apps, how many um
original pieces of software, what have
we created? We've done nothing
whatsoever. With all this this huge pool
of talent, we have only done software
arbitrage, labor arbitrage. It's it's
pathetic the kind of mindset these
people have who are running these
companies. So that's why it's not like
we can't do it but obviously when you
are trying to create new products and
and market those products it's it's it's
risky. The payoff could be huge but the
risk also is there. It's also you may
you stand to lose money sometimes right?
So they don't want any risk. They've got
this tried and tested model of labor
arbitrage which which is bringing them
money. So they've been okay with that.
But now things are bad. things are bad
because of the advent of AI and in five
years time it's going to be who knows
could be curtain for the Indian IT
industry it could be so it's because of
this attitude that we have not been able
to build companies like AWS or whatever
because they have never wanted to do
something different
says every nation on big daddy US's
earth as of now suffers from illegal
immigration including the US the
invisible hand speaks a certain
language. Well, that is something you
claim. I I
uh we don't have any uh evidence that
goes in that direction. Okay. So, I'm
going to just say all right if you say
so.
Kumar Kanesk says as India is close to
finding massive oil reserves in the
Andaman Sea. There are news of American
giants like Shell etc. to acquire Bhat
Petroleum. Is this a red flag? I think
Bat Petroleum is it a is it a
governmentowned company? Barat Petroleum
is it a state-owned company? Let's let's
find out. Barat Petroleum
Petroleum
is it stateowned? It's a Fortune 500
etc. Indian public sector headquartered.
It's the governmentowned.
It's a government-owned company. It's
India's second largest government-owned
downstream oil producer.
Okay. So Bhat petroleum is owned by by
the government of India.
I if you have heard news of uh American
giants like Shell or whatever trying to
acquire this well as long as the
government of India doesn't want to sell
it, it won't work. It won't work like
that. It doesn't work like that. Right?
Uh now when it comes to these this news
of India being close to finding massive
oil reserves in the say well let's not
count our chickens before they hatch.
Okay? We haven't seen any actual news of
a gigantic uh oil discovery. So until
that news is announced and we actually
find something, let's not talk about
that. I mean it's pointless. I have been
saying for the longest time myself that
you know gigantic subcontinent sized
nation like India, it's inconceivable
that we won't have gigantic oil reserves
in various parts of the country or off
of of the of the continental shelf in
the ocean. It's inconceivable. But
having those reserves hidden somewhere
is pointless. We've got to find them,
right? And right now there are people
talking about, you know, we are on the
verge of making a huge oil discovery.
Well, discover it and then talk about
it. That's what I would say.
Okay. Uh Rashi Kudin says, "Is India
cautious about Bangladesh subs? They
want six more from Korea." You mean
Bangladesh submarines?
Bangladesh want six more submarines from
from Korea. Well, I suppose Korea I I
suppose you mean South Korea.
Well, let the Bangladeshes do whatever
they want. That is their their internal
matter. If they want more submarines,
let them buy the submarines. If they
acquire the submarines, well, it's going
to be a long drawn out process. And if
obviously now Bangladesh is a vasal of
the US, it's East Pakistan now. So, if
they acquire submarines, even though
they face no threat for anybody, it
means it's a threat to us. So we will
obviously take appropriate steps uh to
circumvent such threats and and uh
potentially neutralize them if required.
So we we'll look into that if this
happens.
Shva said Sherva says the western
governments are moving towards
censorship under the protect of pretext
of kids safety acts. What are the global
repercussions other than mass
surveillance in the UK? protest videos
against censored
uh are censored.
Okay. Um yeah, the west the western
governments are indeed moving towards
censorship. Uh not so much in the US
that that much right now but definitely
in nations like the UK and various EU
nations. We have we are witnessing the
passing of various laws and rules and
regulation. Um, in the UK, uh, you you
stand to spend more jail time for
putting a meme on social media than for
actually doing some kind of actual
crime. Yeah. Some some real world crime.
So that's the kind of dystopian,
you know, situation we are these nations
are moving towards. So if you're in the
UK and you post certain things on social
media, you go to jail, the cops come and
knock on your door and you you are
thinking bad thoughts and you need to go
go to jail. It's very much like u that
book, right? The dystopian book by
George Orwell 1984.
Um thought crime. Thought crime. So
there's absolutely no freedom of speech
if you have such such laws, right? Uh so
censorship is becoming kind of the norm.
And uh I don't know about the kids
safety acts. I have not looked into that
but there are various kinds of
censorship that's that's that are
becoming more and more prevalent. What's
the global repercussions of this other
than mass surveillance? Well, if that
infection spreads to other countries, it
becomes a you know the whole n the whole
world becomes a morass of censorship and
uh people will then have to be very
watchful about what they say and what
they post on social media and so on. So
that means that that people will have to
take uh resort to some other measures to
express themselves or maybe they can't
express themselves at all. Uh thankfully
that's not the case in across the entire
world. There are still countries where
you can to a reasonable extent express
yourself, right?
But if if there are there's this global
outbreak of of censorship, well that's
bad. It means the world has become has
regressed. it's become more total. It it
would indicate that the world is
becoming a more totalitarian place, a
more authoritarian kind of uh world and
that well that's not that's not good for
everybody, right? It's it's bad for
everybody. You can't have the free
exchange of thoughts and ideas. You
can't have free and fair dialogue. It's
it's it's a good it's a good practice
for people with opposing views to be
able to speak freely and and have a
dialogue so that they understand each
other's perspectives. That's what you
have in a free and open world. That's
what the West calls the liberal world
order, but they are in the process of
dismantling it, which which is
unfortunate. Um yeah, so the UK seems to
be the flag bearer of all these things
right now, which is well unfortunate,
isn't it? Joshua Lawrence says 150.
Well, all right sir and thank you for
your contribution.
Um Rohan Suna says my views on the
shameless BCCI playing cricket with
Pakistan. Well, I have made it very
clear that I am not in favor of playing
anything any any kind of sporting
sporting there should be no sporting
contact with Pakistan. Look, do you
remember folks, South Africa was uh
banned from participating in
international sports for more than two
decades because of their uh policy of
practicing apathide of of treating their
majority population as secondass
citizens right South Africa you may
remember that they were banned from
cricket as well and it's only after they
dismantled the system of apathide that
South Africa was welcome back welcomed
back into the uh global sporting um
fraternity and their first uh cricket
series after re-entering re-entering the
the global world order was against
India. It was a three one-day match
series against India which which India
won 2-1 uh if I'm not mistaken. So India
was the nation to welcome them back with
open hands with open arms. So South
Africa was banned for practicing
apathide but Pakistan practices
practices something much worse. Pakistan
practices terrorism. I think Pakistan
needs to be banned from any kind of
sport. There should be a blanket blanket
ban on Pakistan.
They should not be allowed to partic
participate in any international
sporting activity and India should
ensure this happens. That's all I'll
say. I'll not comment about the BCCI or
any such thing. But that's what needs to
happen. And the government of India and
the BCC have the power to compel all
other cricket boards from not to to not
to not engage with Pakistan in any
bilateral cricket engagements and we can
ensure that Pakistan stays is is removed
from multilateral tournaments as well.
That's actually what needs to happen.
That's what I would say.
Um Nachiket J Raman says what's the deep
state's end game with DJT Donald J.
Trump three and a half more years. Well,
Donald J. Trump is obviously uh tasked
with reshaping
reshaping the world order, the world
economic order and the world the global
order is overall. So the the US once
constructed something that they have
until recently been calling the
rules-based world order, the westernled
liberal world order, the rules-based
world order. Right? Well, I've always
said this even before Donald Trump came
back for the second term that the
rules-based world order is a whimsbased
based world order. They make up the
rules as they go along and whenever they
feel like they'll change the rules.
Well, that's what's happening now.
Donald J. Trump, his his task over the
next three and a half years during his
four-year term is to completely reshape
the global uh order, the the trading
order, the financial economic order and
overall the the relationships between
the US and all other nations. That's
what the objective is. Uh so the US is
going to be much more harsh now towards
other nations. is going to treat allies
also with with this bully sort of
behavior, bullying behavior, arm
twisting behavior. It's going to extract
way more from allies.
Um and uh it's it's a world order that
we are witnessing the bifurcation of. Uh
so it's it's all to do with the with the
economic rise of China and technological
rise of China and the US obviously sees
that as a very worrying uh development
and uh also India is also showing signs
of you know if India is left alone for
the long term India will also become a
major economy. Uh so the and the
objective is to completely reshape the
world order. Uh so that's what DJT is
doing and in the next three and a half
years it's going to be a very different
world.
Okay. Uh Kapay developer says what's the
path to generate divergent tech trees.
Uh the rest of the world seems to play
catch up with the leader. Is this an
inherent tribal trait?
Look, when it comes to creating
divergent tech trees,
uh, look, the the US is obviously the
the technological leader in the world,
uh, and it it has created all the
platforms and all the technologies that
the that the world consumes, right? Uh,
the products may be may be manufactured
elsewhere, but the products are still
American products. So all these
technology platforms like YouTube, like
Facebook, like Google, like uh Chat GBT,
OpenAI, like like uh Anthropic and
whatever else you can think of, all of
that is American. All of the major cell
phone oss, operating systems, it's
either iOS or or Android. If it's if
it's if Android is is a derivative of
Linux, let's say, well, Linux is also
was also developed in the West, which
the US is the overlord of. So it's the
western thing and the Chinese have tried
their best to create their own uh
parallel uh technological ecosystem uh
behind the great firewall. So uh they
also have created operating systems for
phones Android style operating systems
maybe by forking Linux or whatever and
they are trying to create their own uh
semiconductor thing and all that the
semiconductor development ecosystem
their own photo lithography machines and
whatnot. So the Chinese are trying to
create their own independent thing and
they are succeeding rather well at that.
But when it comes to the rest of the
world like you're saying like India etc.
we just following the leader uh
following the leader being a consumer
rather than a producer and when it comes
to India when we saying that we are
developing technologies we are
essentially like you say playing
catch-up. So we are trying to develop
jet jet engines the kind of jet engines
that were developed 40 years ago 30
years ago in the west. we are trying to
develop uh fighter planes. The kind of
fighter planes were developed a long
time ago in the west and so on. So it's
to some extent because of pacivity to
some extent because of of an inferiority
complex and so on. So what's the path?
Forget about the rest of the world.
Let's talk about India. What's the path?
We need to have our own uh indigenous
technological uh ecosystem. We need to
have our own see Silicon Valley kinds of
places where you can attract the best
talent. not overt tax them, not overwork
them, not overregulate them, let them
do, let them do stuff, let them break
stuff, let them create, let them try,
let them fail, let some of them succeed.
Um, incentivize them for succeeding.
Incentivize them for for trying. Don't
penalize them for failing. And not just
software, but also hardware. All of this
needs to happen. Um, and it's it's I
think it's the government's job and task
to to make this happen, I would say.
Yeah.
Okay. Joshua Lawrence says the US has
deployed two nuclear submarines near
Russian waters if Russia's submarine
fleet hypothetic is Russia's submarine
fleet hypo okay if Russia's submarine
fleet hypothetically surrounds the US
submarines how does this play out okay
look Mr. Trump he announced a couple of
days ago or maybe yesterday maybe maybe
day before yesterday whenever he did he
announced that first of all he he he
objected to uh the Russian politician
Mr. Dimitri Medvev's recent
pronouncements on social media he said
that Mr. Medv is playing a very
dangerous game and you better be careful
in that sort of thing you know issuing
threats Mr. Medvev is the former is a
former Russian president
um and then Mr. Trump said that since
Mr. Meduv is is threatening nuclear war
whatever so that's why I have taken the
decision to deploy two uh of my nuclear
assets nuclear submarines uh to the
appropriate places wherever it is
so people are consuming that to mean
that the US is deploying two nuclear
submarines near Russian waters. Well my
dear friends let me tell you something.
Let me break some news to you. US
submarines are always deployed in
forward locations.
Always deployed in in regions that are
not far from Russian waters.
Always
US US nuclear submarines are always on
patrol across the world in the various
oceans in the Pacific Ocean in the
Atlantic Ocean in the Indian Ocean.
the South China Sea most likely the sea
of I don't know about that but it's all
over the place and nuclear submarines
especially advanced ones like what the
Americans have they have very long
endurance what is what is what does
endurance mean it means the time they
can spend at sea without needing
resupplying or refueling so they first
of all they use nuclear reactors for
their propulsion right nuclear
propulsion which means that they
essentially have unlimited legs long
legs because they don't need to be
refueled. I mean the refueling is done
once in a few years. So the nuclear
reactor has sufficient fuel for to last
several years actually and they can
recycle the air which means the carbon
dioxide that is exhailed by humans is
recycled into oxygen. They have uh
mechanisms for that and they can carry
enough food supplies to last let's say 6
months. So they are on on mission for
sometimes 6 months at a time. So they
can go all across the world and uh the
these nuclear submarines are an integral
part of America's second strike
capability. What's what do we mean by
the second strike capability? In case an
adversary is able to launch nuclear
strikes in the US and uh destroy the
US's ability to launch retaliatory
strikes, then the nuclear submarines
will do the job. And one nuclear
submarine typically has enough uh
ballistic missiles with nuclear warheads
to destroy an entire continent. So
that's the deal. So these nuclear
submarines are always deployed all
across the world. So this is I mean so
then what does it mean that he's saying
that? What does he what is he trying to
say? He's just uh expressing
displeasure.
There's always a cat and mouse game
going on between nuclear between the
submarines of the various major powers.
Okay. Russia also has a very powerful
nuclear submarine fleet and there are
various kinds of sub nuclear submarines.
Some are ballistic missile submarines,
some are attack submarines, hunter
killer submarines and so on. So
typically when a ballistic missile
submarine is on a longrange patrol,
you're going to have some other nations
submarines trailing it, detect, trying
to detect and trying to see where it's
going. It's always a cat and mouse game.
It's always going on right now as we
speak. Right now as we speak, it's
happening. It's happening in the Indian
Ocean as well. We also have our nuclear
submarines on on patrol right now. And
that's how it goes. So that's how it
plays out. It's an ongoing cat and mouse
game. Right now as we speak there are
submarines dozens of sub submarines
on patrol on duty.
Sabikwar. Thank you very much sir. Thank
you sir.
Ishan Mukhi says, "If the US hadn't
gotten its got got its independence from
the UK, how would the British Empire no
would the British would the British
Empire have created nukes and become a
mega superpower even with colonies till
date?" Okay.
So
um if the US had not received its
independence or won its independence
from the UK
even then the world would be run by the
same empire that we have today but it
would be perhaps headquartered in in in
London or maybe the British Empire would
have decided that you know we have this
huge continent that we own that we've
captured by genociding the natives by
stealing the land. let's move our
capital to the to the to north to North
America and they may have possibly
created a capital city somewhere in
North America and uh eventually they may
also have created nukes depending on the
threat perception and so on. Um yeah. So
so we have to understand that the US
empire is nothing but a continuation of
the British Empire. And if the US empire
had not been created, it would have been
the British Empire that would have been
ruling the world right now. Maybe from
London, maybe from somewhere in the in
the in in in the continent of North
America.
Uh now the question you to ask yourself
is why did the US first of all how were
the first nuclear weapons created? Well,
all of that happened because of the
discovery of of quantum mechanics in the
early 1900s. And then once you start
understanding quantum mechanics and you
start probing the atomic structure of
various um elements and when you move up
the chain and you come to the heavier
elements and you discover the properties
of uranium and the unstable nature and
what a slowmoving neutron can do if it
hits a uranium nucleus and then you see
that that a chain reaction is possible
then naturally you will want to
weaponize it.
Hm.
So even if the British Empire had
persisted and no American empire had
been created, as long as quantum
mechanics was discovered in the early
1900s, somebody would have come up with
nuclear weapons. And most likely it
would have been the UK. And uh, of
course, the Manhattan project happened
during the Second World War when the US
wanted this this tremendous asymmetric
advantage that nobody else would have.
That's why they did that out of war
footing and it was Mr. Dr. J. Robert
Oppenheimer who was at the helm of the
project. So yeah, I think it would have
happened anyway.
Prashant says, "Aren't Indian drug drug
manufacturers immune to tariffs?" I am
not sure if Trump's tariffs exclude
Indian drug manufacturers. uh it is
indeed true that India supplies about
40% of the generic generic drugs that
the US uh as a nation uh let's say
consumes. So yeah 40% of the America of
America's generic drugs are supplied
from India. U I'm not sure if Trump has
imposed tariffs on India's drug
manufacturers. Uh they do need that. So,
so let's say hypothetically uh India
stops tomorrow uh the export of of these
drugs to the US. It will create an
immediate healthcare crisis in the US.
Immediate and America's public will
blame whom? They will blame Donald J.
Trump for that. He'll try and portray
India as the bad guy. But we'll make it
very clear that we are doing this in
response to whatever tariffs, punitive
tariffs, etc. Trump has imposed on us.
It's you who started this. we are simply
responding because we have there has to
be some reciprocity. You take action,
I'll take action. Um
so um it's it's not good for the US if
that happens, right? So that's one uh
example of the kind of leverage that
India does have. Obviously the US has
way more leverage than India, but we
also have some leverage and and generic
drugs are one of those uh factors that
we have. Uh so I'm not sure if Trump has
uh imposed tariffs. Uh let's let's try
and find out. Let's try and find out if
he has. I think he's imposed blanket
tariffs, right? I think he has imposed
blanket blanket tariffs on
almost everything. Has he has he
has he uh exempted certain products from
the tariffs? I'm not sure. I'll not go
and do the research now because we're
doing a live stream. But check it out,
guys. Ladies, ladies and gents, please
check it out.
Nearby says, "Recently, the US has
struck a one-sided deal with the EU and
Japan. Even Indonesia, by the way, were
pretty one-sided. Why do people in these
countries not realize that they have
been vasalized?
They were always
there were always vasals." And okay,
let's not talk about Japan for for now.
Briefly, let's talk about the EU only.
The EU, the European Union. What is the
European Union? It's a conglomeration of
nations
all
vasalized by the US. When did the
vasalization happen? It essentially
happened in 1945
when the when the entire continent of
Europe was in ruins and only two powers
existed in Europe. One was the US, the
other was the USSR. So, so that's what
drew the iron curtain and one on the
eastern side of Europe was taken over by
the USSR. The Warsaw packed nations
became the USSR's vasals and the western
nations in Europe became American
vasals.
And it's been such a long-standing
situation that nobody realizes that we
are vasals. But the leaders of the
nations know that and certain nations
chafe against that. Certain nations have
simp most other nations have simply
accepted that as as a feta comply. This
is just the world the way the world is.
Okay. So the nation that chiefs against
American masalhood is is France. The
other nations have simply accepted that
it's the way things are. And uh yeah
when it comes to Japan, well
Japan is not just vasalized, it is under
active permanent US military occupation.
more than 130 permanent US military
bases on Japanese soil. And what the
Japanese people are taught in their
education system in school, college,
university, etc. is that Japan has has
been a very evil country. We did very
very evil things and whatever happened
to us as a consequence was fully
deserved by us. It was karma. So if the
Americans tested two nuclear weapons on
our cities, we deserved it. If the US uh
enslaved us, we deserve it. If the US
run our country today behind the scenes,
we deserve it. And going forward, we
have to be a pacifistic nation. We must
not have an army and we must do whatever
the US tells us because they are better
than us and they are superior to us.
That's that sort of thing. And the
Japanese constitution was written by
Americans.
So once you have the system, how will
people ever realize that they are
vasalized? So that's how it goes. You
see
um Sorup guy says your view on America
on the US importing uranium from Russia
is a hypocrisy. No that's how the world
works. And if you are being hypocritical
it means you you've earned the right to
be hypocritical. Only the powerful can
be hypocritical. You see that's how it
goes. Preach one thing and do the other.
Do something else. Do the opposite of
that. So the US imports uranium from
Russia. Sure. Why does Russia sell it?
Because it's making money out of it. It
has sufficient reserves. Uh excess
reserves possibly. It's not just uranium
that the US imports from Russia. Let me
show you another example. I forget the
name, but I I I'll Google it
immediately.
Okay. Uh rocket engines imported by USA
from Russia.
RD 180.
RD 180. Okay.
So the RD180,
what is this? First flight, etc. A
rocket engine that was designed and
built in Russia. Um, it was developed
for use on the US Atlas 3 and Atlas 5
launch vehicles. It is currently being
phased out due to the national security
implications of reliance on the Russian
built engine. The Americans have tried
their best to reverse engine this,
reverse engineer this engine
and they have tried their best and they
keep on failing. So the Americans still
import this engine from Russia.
So it's not just it's so much more.
Check it out. Okay.
So much more.
Okay. Shesh Sundesh says uh India's
stand in trade tensions shows our deep
strategic roots like Pulashi
who stopped Hershawan
India asserts autonomy not bends to
global powers even if it's smaller and
prouds of roots and bold future
um
I I'm not sure what's the connection
between puli hashwadan and trade
tensions uh you see You have to please
understand my friends that the modernday
nation of India
has tried its best to cut its ties from
the civilizational entity that was bat
that was India. The constitution does
say India that is bat and so on. But our
constitution is entirely western in
nation. It is entirely non-Indian
in nation. Our laws are entirely
non-Indian in in in in nature and
everything about the bureaucracy the
Indian economy the government not the
economy the government governance
machine etc is non-Indian actually we
have tried our best to ape the west
we've tried our best to erase our civil
civilization the education system has
been a big factor in that and so on uh
so if we are standing up to to the to
the bullies today and if we are standing
up for ourselves
it's it's a good thing but it would be
great if we would hearken back even more
to our ancient roots. Uh but it's a good
thing. I'm I'm obviously I'm not
complaining that we are standing up to
the to the west. It's a very good thing.
Ankida says, "What do the West, which is
the NATO alliance, want to achieve out
of the Russia Ukraine war beside
economic benefits from arms deal and
weakening the Russian economy? Uh will
this war ever end? Is it ever going to
end?
So
what does the west want to achieve is
the question. So it was clear as soon as
uh the USSR broke up that the the the US
was not interested in disbanding or
dissolving NATO. NATO was created as a
response to what the US called the
Soviet threat, the communist threat. But
now the USSR was gone and Russia became
a normal democratic nation. They even
adopted democracy, western style
democracy. And they allowed the west to
penetrate their markets and take over
industries. And yet the US did not
dissolve NATO. And they had made a
promise to the Russians that they would
not have NATO expand one inch eastwards.
But they immediately broke the promise
in a couple of years. And they started
expanding eastwards, eastward,
eastwards. And it became clear that
Ukraine was Russia's red line. And the
and the US carried out a coup in
Ukraine. the so-called Euromaidan
revolution which is a coup. It was a
regime change operation. It brought in a
puppet regime, a USbacked regime in
Ukraine and eventually it led to the
Crimean uh situation. Russia annexed,
reanexed, reabsorbed Crimea and then
you've had the Ukraine war which has
been raging since 2022. What's the
objective of the West? The objective of
the West is to weaken Russia. It's to
weaken Russia's economy, what they call
Russia's war economy. and they are
willing to use the people of Ukraine as
cannon foder in their quest to weaken
Russia. Well, from their perspective,
unfortunately, it's not happened because
Russia's actually become stronger as a
as a as a consequence. they have re
reignited their their war machinery that
their military uh industrial uh
ecosystem and their economy has become
stronger as a consequence that GDP has
grown and their their their econom their
military budget has risen way beyond
India's and so on. So the objective was
to drag Russia down, to bog Russia down,
to uh to degrade Russia's economy, to
weaken Russia and if possible effect
regime change in Moscow because Mr.
Putin is a very bad man. Right? So these
are the objectives, but it's not
happened. And now what's the objective?
Just to keep the war dragging on as as
long as possible to keep Russia bogged
down in Ukraine so that it doesn't
become a factor in in the West's
competition with China.
That's the That's the objective. So, the
Ukraine war, it looks like it's going to
go on for a I hope not a decade. It
looks like it's going to go on for
several more years. Why do I say this?
Because they are resupplying Ukraine.
They are they are sending more aid to
Ukraine. The Western nations, including
European nations, they're supplying
Ukraine with more money. They're
supplying Ukraine with long range strike
weapons. And because of that, the
Ukraine government carried out
long-range strikes on Russia. They they
they struck at Russian air bases deep
inside Russian territory. They conducted
operation spider web. It was called
operation spiderweb and so much more. So
it's it's this is this is causing an
escalation of the war and so on. So uh
it looks like the war will go on for a
long time and yeah but the west hasn't
achieved its objective of of weakening
and deg degrading Russia's economy and
the great great great dream was to carry
out regime change in in Moscow not
directly but maybe indirectly. So if the
war is not going well, if Russia's
economy is dragged down, if people are
facing hardships and so on, then
obviously there could be the temptation
in Russia to for for the people to
perhaps carry out a revolution kind of
thing and and and change the government
in in the Kremlin that obviously has not
materialized.
Satellite says if the American deep
state exists, so can we say that their
democracy is fake? And what about India?
How is India's democracy different from
other democracies? Okay, let's do some
kind of comparative analysis. Forget
about the deep state right now. Forget
about the deep state whether it exists
or not. Let's examine America's
democracy structurally.
When you have an election for the
president, okay, we're talking about the
topmost level. We'll not go all the way
down to other levels. Presidential level
democracy. So when we are when American
citizens are voting for the president,
they are voting for two candidates
h and one is from party A, the other is
from party B, Republicans and Democrats.
There's only two parties that matter in
the US. They have some other political
parties for names sake, but those are
insignificant and immaterial. They don't
matter. For all intents and purposes,
the US is a two-party system. two-party
system, two party state and both parties
have essentially the same foreign
policy.
They have different opinions and
different policies and different agendas
when it comes to domestic politics. But
when it comes to external affairs, they
have essentially the same agenda
and they follow the same rule books. So
it's essentially a uniarty system
masquerading as a two-party system. And
even if we say it's a two-party system,
that's just one step above a one party
system like the like like China or North
Korea, right? I mean, why isn't there a
political party that represents the
interests of the African-American
people? Why isn't there a political
party that represents the the interests
of the uh Hispanic people? Why isn't
there a political party that represents
the the interests of the native original
inhabitants of the country? Why aren't
there multiple political parties in each
state in the US like we have in India?
It's not a real democracy. It's an
autocracy masquerading as a democracy.
That's what the US is. It's a police
state. Go to the US. Go to New York
City. See how many cops there are on the
streets. You take those cops away for 15
minutes, there'll be riots.
Okay? That's how it is. It's a police
state. Even Europe is a police state.
I'm talking about Western Europe. It's a
police state. I recently few months ago
met met some EU parliamentary
delegations and some people from Yeah.
And
yeah, some of them did agree privately
that Europe is a police state privately.
They won't say it in open. Um so that's
how it is. So do you call that
democracy? Do you really call that a
democracy? What you have in the US? just
two parties and all both of them
essentially have the same uh foreign
policy. It's not really really
democracy. What's the options that the
people of the US have when it comes to
voting? A or B? And both are essentially
the same. In the US also you have this
political dynasty, the Clintons, the
Bushes. Come on. Come on. What about
India? Well, in India you have got
chaos.
So many political parties.
There's one political party that
represents I mean there are multiple
political parties that represents that
represent the interests of each little
community or so-called cast or religion.
Each state has multiple political
parties. My goodness, you have a couple
of political parties that are considered
to be national parties and there are so
many other political parties all over
the place. It's chaotic. It's a mess but
it's real democracy and it's is it good
for the country? That's a different
story, right? So India is a genuine
democracy, a vibrant democracy,
a messy democracy.
Yeah. Uh so that's how India India's
democracy is different. In other
countries like France, the UK etc. you
have multiple parties, more than two,
more than two. But even then, even there
it's quite managed. In India it's not
managed. It's anybody can start a
political party tomorrow and you know if
you have the money you can do that. So
it's so we don't even have to discuss
the deep state in in this context.
Okay.
Okay. Kunar Kumar Kumar Kaneshka says as
the US is now gearing against India
openly
for sanctions well it's they're calling
it tariffs for now. So for tariffs
will it hamper
excuse me.
So will it hamper India's defense
procurement like Sukoy 57 S500 all of
which are essential for defense? Look
the Americans are expressing tremendous
displeasure over the fact that India is
buying Russian oil and uh other
connections with Russia and so on. So
they want India to cut all ties with
Russia otherwise there's a threat of
potentially 500% tariffs. So the US is
is being very tough with India. The
Trump administration is being very tough
with India right now. They are adopting
a variety of maximalist stances in the
diplomatic negotiations for a so-called
trade deal. Right?
And obviously what they want is India
should become US facile which means cut
all ties with Russia. Stop buying stop
purchasing Russian oil. Stop purchasing
Russian weapons. Uh only purchase
American weapons, purchase oil from
America and do everything the the
Americans say. Be a good boy, little
doggy, good dog. That's what they want.
uh India will not do that no matter what
happens. So it's going to be uh a it's
going to be tough days for India because
the Americans are obviously way more
powerful. Uh will this hamper India's
defense procurement? Look, we have now
clear said it very clearly to the US. We
are not going to purchase your godamned
F-35s, those what flying trash cans. We
will not purchase those aircraft. But we
need something as a stop gap measure
until we have the AMCA becoming a viable
you know becoming entering serial
production which should be maybe around
2030 something by 2035 we should have
reasonable numbers of that hopefully. So
we have a decade to go in the in in the
interim. We need some stop gap
arrangement.
We need some uh some decent numbers of
fifth generation fighter planes. So that
would I most likely with the Suka 57.
Otherwise we can buy a bunch of Rafal
maybe 100 plus Rafals which also could
perhaps make sense. But but I would say
we should go for the Suka 57. It will
really infuriate Donald Trump and the
Americans. But we need the aircraft and
we can't go for the F-35.
for a variety of reasons be beyond the
trade thing and all that. So it would
have to be the Fuka 57. It's going to be
a very tough choice for India. A very
hard decision to make but India will
need to make that decision. Otherwise we
have this tremendous shortfall of
aircraft squadrons. The Pakistanis have
nearly as many squadrons as India.
India is economically like not anywhere
near Pakistani. We are a much more
gigantic economy but we still have
almost the same number of aircraft
squadrons as Pakistan. This is
unbelievable and something needs to be
done about that immediately. So India
needs to quickly acquire a significant
number of fighter planes right and
there's news about the Pakist
potentially supplying Pakistan with
fighter planes and whatnot fifth
generation fighter planes which will
make the situation even more dire for
India and the US is very happy about
that. They're okay with Pakistan being
like I said in bed with China. So India
will have to procure quickly fighter
planes. We cannot dillydally for for
another couple of years. The decision
will have to be made very soon.
So will Trump's u actions the Trump
regime's actions hamper India's defense
procurement? I hope not. It should not.
Otherwise we we are setting ducks to our
enemies. Also the S500 I'm not sure if
India is considering the F S S500 U
India is developing its own S400 S500
kind of system which is good but if we
have a shortfall if we have a
requirement in the interim interim time
period maybe we should even go for the
S500 the S500 will be clearly an
improvement over the already excellent
S400 so I think it makes sense if if we
have that requirement of that sort of
system more numbers maybe we can go for
the S500 Look, if it displeases the US,
it is what it is. We've got to do what
is u in line with our national interest.
And that's what the government has been
saying the past few days, ever since
Trump announced those tariffs that India
will take what will do whatever it takes
to safeguard India's national interest
and the interests of India's citizens,
which is good.
Suchin Kumar says, "How credible is
mutually assured destruction? Mad in an
age of precisiong guided conventional
weapons. It is still very credible.
Mutually assured destruction. What is
this concept? It's a concept that
emerged
in the previous cold war, the 20th
centuries cold war. So the US had
developed nuclear weapons. The USSR
went ahead and quickly developed its own
nuclear weapons. Then both nations
started developing ballistic missiles,
you know, delivery systems. The Soviets
uh they they had various options when it
comes to delivering nuclear weapons to
the destination long range uh strategic
bombers also uh ballistic missiles. both
nations the US and USSR uh employed Nazi
former Nazi uh rocket engineers and
that's how they developed their their
own space programs and so the the
concept emerged that you know both
nations can destroy the other.
So, so the the the the the logic which
essentially comes from game theory was
that you know uh
the the presence of so many nuclear
weapons ensured that both nations can't
go to war because if one nuclear weapon
is launched
then then the receiving nation will
immediately launch its own strike
package before that nuclear weapon even
lands. the missile even lands and then
if you if this nation launches a
retaliatory strike package then the
other nation will again launch more
missiles and it's going to be a salvo
from both sides and both nations will
end up being destroyed. So that's
mutually assured destruction. So both
nations ensured that they maintained
stockpiles of up to 10,000 nuclear
warheads each which assured the other
that if you attack me I'm going to
attack you and we will both be
destroyed. And then there was there was
the concept of second strike and so on
which because of which you had uh
nuclear submarines permanently on patrol
which would ensure that even if all the
nuclear missiles on on ground are
destroyed the submarines would ensure
that the other the offensive country was
destroyed. So that is mutually assured
destruction which essentially prevents
war from happening but it is so
dangerous of the world. A false alarm or
something can can end up creating a
cascade of events which will destroy the
world. So that's mutually assured
destruction. Does that concept still
exist today? Absolutely.
Absolutely it still exists today. Even
if you have precision guided
conventional weapons
even then the concept exists. India and
China. Let's take that example. Forget
about the US and Russia today. India and
China. Uh it is said that India has
about 180 nuclear warheads. That's what
the west claims. Well, did they come and
examine our warheads? I mean what the
hell? How do you know? But let's say
let's imagine we have 180 and the
Chinese have what 600 like the West
says.
You don't need
180 warheads to destroy a country.
You don't need that. Uh so in the
context of India and China, India has
extremely precise
uh ballistic missiles and other kinds of
missiles. We know that we saw that
during operation sindur the precision
with with which we hit our targets. The
targets were just across the border just
Pakistan just a couple of kilometers 100
km or something 200 300 km away from
where they were launched. But uh our
missiles are extremely accurate even at
longer distances. Uh so we have very
precise conventional weapons, precision
guided conventional weapons. I expect
the Chinese also have very precise
precision guided conventional weapons.
Um cruise missiles, ballistic missiles,
whatnot. Yeah.
So let's say India and China
hypothetically go to war. We never want
it to happen but hypothetically. And we
use conventional weapons very precise
bam bam. So India strikes at China's
assets in Tibet. China's occup strikes
at whatever assets they want to strike
at and we see how it goes. But let's say
things go bad for either country and
then they think of using nuclear
weapons. Then what happens and the other
country also has nuclear weapons and the
means to deliver them. Both countries
have ballistic missiles with the whole
other country in its complete range.
Then both countries have MIRV equipped
ballistic missiles which is one missile
containing multiple warheads and the
warheads can go in different directions
and be targeted independently. So if a
nuclear exchange happens it will end up
destroying both countries fully.
Everything China or India has spent
decades building up will be destroyed.
So that is mutually assured destruction
and it exists. It is it is credible and
it is relevant even in this age of
precisiong guided conventional weapons.
All right.
Rahul says should we implement a law
like GDPR which with clauses that make
it mandatory for companies to partner
with local cloud partners store data
within India? I think it's a good idea.
I don't know what GDPR is. Let me just
quickly Google that. What is GDPR? Let
me see. All right. GDPR.
What is that? GDPR. General data
protection regulation. A European Union
law focused on data privacy and
security. It sets guidelines on how
organizations collect, process, and
protect personal information of
individuals within the EU. When enacted
within the EU, long story, so I'll not
go and read the whole thing. But uh if
it if if the law makes it mandatory for
companies to partner with local cloud
providers and store data within the host
country, it makes a lot of sense. Yep.
So depending on how things go with the
US, we could and we should enact a law
and implement it like what you what you
are mentioning here.
Um okay says please teach us system
think systems thinking and design
thinking. Is it if possible make a
playlist just like understanding
America? it would help many young
entrepreneurs. Okay, thank you for the
suggestion. I will consider it
seriously. Systems thinking and design
thinking. Yeah, it's something that is
very important. So, I I will take this
into account. Thank you, sir.
Rajith Lalit says big fan of your work,
sir. Thank you for the all the
knowledge. Well, you're very welcome.
It's my pleasure and thank you so much,
sir.
Geopolitical Dubai says, why does Russia
have only one aircraft carrier? Well,
that's a good question. Why does Russia
have only one aircraft carrier?
First of all,
we have to understand aircraft carriers
aren't useful in contested waters
and it's it's a huge enticing target. So
that's one thing. Russia is a
continental empire. Let's let's Google
let's go let's not Google. Let's go to
the map. Sorry. Let us go to map and
let's take a look at Russia.
So we're talking about Russia here. the
country that sprawls across Eurasia. To
the north of Russia, you have what looks
like the ocean, but if we look at uh
satellite images, you will see it's it's
mostly ice.
It's mostly ice. If we if we zoom in,
okay, this is not satellite images. What
is this
um terrain? I would like to say
satellite.
Okay, it's not doing a good job of
showing us the satellite imagery. But if
we zoom in, you will find that it is
mostly ice. It's mostly ice and snow.
It's all it's all frozen. Why are Zlia
where they tested the Tar Bomba back in
the 1960s or something 50 megaton? Uh so
Russia is a continental empire,
continental entity and its threat
perception, its major threats lie on
land. The major threats are west west of
Russia which is the EU and NATO nations
and the other major threat for Russia is
down south which is China and uh so
Russia and and other threats over here
obviously are the hidden threats which
are submarines. So Russia doesn't have
any hegemonic ambitions right now. Uh
aircraft carriers are employed by
hegemonic nations for the purpose of
projecting power and terrorizing
the nations that see the aircraft
carriers. An aircraft carrier is is a
threat. It's a massive threat, but it's
not something you employ in contested
waters because it's so so tempting to
hit. I mean, the loss of an aircraft car
is such a disaster for a nation's
morale. So, because of these reasons and
also perhaps because of uh budgetary
constraints
uh etc. that's why Russia has only one
aircraft carrier. It's not that
important for Russia. Russia has
tremendously dangerous submarines and
that's where the real threat for its
adversaries lies.
Anonymous scientist says Musk compared
Elon Musk compared the capabilities of
different space agencies and the time
their best vehicle would take to reach
Mars. He intentionally excluded IshRO.
Why does the West downplay India's
achievements? Some sinister plan?
There's no sinister plan. Um it's just
the West doesn't like India.
The west doesn't like India. There is a
deeprooted
uh annoyance let's say with India. Why
does India still exist? The west
destroyed the entire world in the past
500 years. They destroyed entire
civilizations, entire cultures. Look at
Africa. Does any country in Africa
practice its indigenous culture and
independence system of governance
anymore? Indigenous religions? Nothing.
Everything's been wiped out. There's
just two foreign religions across
Africa. This is a smattering of people
here and there who practice some local
African religions and they those people
are demonized. They're called what? Uh
practicing witchcraft or or occult or uh
ritualism or something and those people
are typically treated like criminals in
Africa. So the west has destroyed entire
cultures. They've enslaved entire
nations. Look at Japan enslaved. Look at
South Korea enslaved. Look at South
Korea. Where is Buddhism today in South
Korea? Almost wiped out.
They have done that to everybody. They
enslaved India for a for two and a half
centuries and India still not destroyed.
That that deeply annoys the west and the
west hates polytheism despite them
originally being a polytheistic culture
which was smashed out by Christianity in
over the past 1500 years or so.
Polytheism was smashed out of the west
brutally. Brutally
So the west hates India for that. They
hate polytheism. They don't understand
polytheism. They consider it satanic and
so on. And these Indians, these these
brown Indian Hindus who we ruled for two
and a half centuries, they dare stand up
again on their own feet and they dare
launch rockets into space. So there's
this this hatred, right? This deep deep
uh jealousy, annoyance, whatever. And
that's why they like to exclude India.
So yeah, sometimes and and and sometimes
it is done without realizing what you're
doing, but it's there deep down.
Uh Twinkle Barbados says, "What's the
long-term solution to the Bangladesh
issue?" The long-term issue, long-term
solution to all issues in the
subcontinent is for India to grow, India
to rise, India to become so powerful
that all the um all the children of
mother India eventually want to return
to the fold of mother India. India has
to become
extremely powerful economically and
otherwise technologically
and culturally in the ter in in the
matter of science technology in the
matter of culture and civilization
economically also India has to become a
space fairing power India has to lead
the world in everything
once we start doing that even if we are
one-third of the way there all solutions
or all problems will automatically start
getting resolved The long-term solution
to all of India's problems is for India
to rise again significantly, not be um
an also ran player. India should be the
main player, not an NPC like they say,
right? India has historically the since
47 been an NPC. Now India is showing
signs of aspiring to be a main player, a
central character and that's what Yeah.
Okay. So that's what needs to happen.
Vive Singh says, "Can the US throw
Taiwan as a carrot to China and engage
them in a long war like Russia Ukraine?"
Well, actually the US won't mind that.
The US won't mind
China getting embroiled in a war in
Taiwan. But then the question is who
does China fight for Taiwan?
If it's Taiwan alone,
then China can take care of Taiwan. But
if the US
supports Taiwan and that's what causes
the war to go on, well, that's a direct
confrontation between China and the US,
which is dangerous. Uh so when it comes
to Ukraine,
it's all the supplies for Ukraine etc.
are coming in from the NATO nations, not
directly from the US. It's coming via
NATO. There is no NATO like structure
in the Taiwan region. You have South
Korea which is a US occupied country.
You have Japan but they don't want to
get embroiled in any war. If the US
wants they can obviously embroil South
Korea and Japan in a war about Taiwan. I
mean let me show the map. If you look at
the map,
if you look at the map, see we have
Taiwan here. And you see the Japanese
islands near Taiwan. See Yaguni. This is
the island of Yonaguni which is a
Japanese island right just a few about a
100 or so maybe 150 or so kilometers
from Taiwan
yeah 113 kilometers from Taiwan so Japan
is right next to Taiwan let's say China
makes a move on Taiwan the question is
who defends Taiwan the US has sufficient
naval naval power to cause huge problems
for China
u but is it possible for the US to keep
a war with China going on for a for a
few years over Tai Taiwan, I think it's
pretty difficult. So, so Taiwan is a
different situation. If you just if you
just look at the geography, you will
realize that it's a different situation.
Of course, the US could bring in South
Korea and and Japan into the mix, but it
would not be good for South Korea or
Japan. Those two nations could also get
end up getting significantly damaged as
a consequence.
Um, Arinagi says, "Have you watched
Narima film ball?" Okay, we're not
discussing movies today. We're
discussing only geopolitics. Very sorry.
I will only take geopolitics questions
today. I apologize, but that's that's
the rule, right? Look at the pin
comment. So, maybe you can ask this
question in in a future live stream. All
right. Thank you.
Kajuro Bitter Thornne says, "Will India
have more room to maneuver after the
2026 midterms in the US? Surely the
Republicans will lose their majorities.
Or is it is trade policy all in the
executive's hands. I think the trade
policy is mostly in the executive's
hands. And even if there's the the
Republicans lose their majority in the
House or Senate or whatever, uh I think
trade policy is still in the executive's
hands. Of course, if the Republicans
lose their majorities, it will make
Donald Trump a rather diminished
president and uh his actions will then
not be that popular. his his image will
have diminished and obviously it it will
make things kind of easier for India
definitely even if uh the trade policy
remains in the executive's hands but if
the executive itself is weakened the
president himself is kind of weakened
and he loses some of his aura and and
and and uh strength and power etc in the
US it will probably give India more room
to maneuver so yeah we will have to wait
and watch I think we should wait until
the 2026 midterms in the US. I think we
should continue our trade negotiations
with the US which we are doing. Uh we
have been very our government has been
very mature. We haven't thrown a tantrum
like Trump has thrown. We haven't backed
down from the trade talks. We has we
have said that you know we want to reach
a mutually acceptable beneficial trade
deal with the US and we are continuing
our negotiations. So let us continue the
negotiations and don't give into the
maximalist demands of the US and keep it
going as long as required. we cannot
exceed to all of their demands
and if that ensure that our the trade
negotiations go on for a long time let
it be so it will obviously frustrate
Trump but yeah uh what you're mentioning
is is a is very important things will
most likely change after the 2026
midterms and that will probably give
India uh more room for maneuvering
nilast says uh among the top four armies
except for China All armies are battleh
hardened. Why PLA is not involved in any
any conflicts? China must be knowing the
benefits of being involved in a
conflict. Still they boast that they can
take Arunachal or beat the US. What you
are saying makes uh significant sense.
The last time China, the Chinese army,
the so-called PLA, people's liberation
army, the last time it was engaged in an
actual conflict was 1979. Let's take a
look.
um here.
So in 197 in the 1970s
um Cambodia
was taken over by the Kir Rouge which
was a Chinesebacked
leftist Mauist gerilla outfit. They took
over Cambodia and unleashed a horrific
genocide on the people of Cambodia.
Horrific.
No words. That's how bad it was. So
Vietnam which was a communist nation
eventually I think in 78 or 79 you can
look at they invaded Cambodia and
liberated Cambodia from the Kir Rouge.
So they defeated a Chinesebacked
terrorist organization essentially
genocidal organization and to punish
Vietnam for defeating the Kir Rouge
China invaded Vietnam from the north.
The Chinese PLA invaded Vietnam and they
thought they will quickly overrun
Vietnam and teach the Vietnamese a
lesson. But what actually happened was
unthinkable for China because the
Vietnamese gave the Chinese a resounding
defeat. It was it was a humiliation for
the PLA. So the PLA was defeated roundly
and soundly by the Vietnamese given a
absolutely bloody nose in 1979. In 1987
there was a clash between India and
China I think in Arunachal Pradesh and
India won that clash. The Chinese were
defeated in that as well. Uh so since
there was not a major conflict obviously
it was a series of localized clashes. Uh
but since 1979 essentially the Chinese
PLA has not been involved in any
conflict. They are not battle hardened.
They are not battle tested at all. They
don't even have any insurgencies or any
separatist movements or any such thing
that they've been battling. So,
so the question you're asking is why
doesn't the PLA get involved in any
conflicts? Well, they don't want to.
There are benefits of being involved in
conflicts because you it it battle tests
you. It allows you to tests to test your
new weapons
u and see their strengths and
weaknesses. it it it battle hardens your
soldiers all of that but the question is
who does China fight with
it means they will have to initiate some
conflict somewhere well there are
drawbacks to initiating conflicts right
you may get beaten again so that's the
deal so obviously they will boast China
is a nation that is great at propaganda
they'll boost that they can beat
everybody take Arunach or whatever well
well please try it please do try if you
want to yeah so there you have there you
have
Um, Nav Nu2 car says, "Why Russian
invasion of Hostol airport day one of
war failed?
What lessons can we learn if we need to
do a similar airbridge operation in
Scarardo in the future?" What is host?
I'm not sure of this hostel thing. Let
me check it out. Russian invasion of
Hosttol airport. What is hostile
airport?
Hosttol airport. What happened there?
Battle of Hostto airport was a military
engagement that happened at this airport
during the Kiev offensive. Okay. In
early 2024.
Yeah. On 24th February this special
military operation started and 24 25
February 2022 this thing happened and
what Russia failed did it at this
battle. What was the outcome? result
occupation of this thing by Russia until
2nd April
uh and so on unexpected nuclear okay so
it looks like Russia tried to take this
and they were foiled at that so I
haven't analyzed the battle I don't know
why it failed uh
so I'm not sure what lessons became
wrong I will have to read the whole
thing analyze it and then draw
conclusions from that I haven't done
that and during a live stream I will not
spend waste your time by sitting five
minutes and reading the whole thing. So
I'm sorry I can't answer the question
because I haven't studied this.
All right. Uh but what what lessons can
we learn if we need to do a similar
airbridge operation in Scardu in the
future? Uh I would say look don't try to
do airbridge operations at all. Conquer
whatever you want to conquer and absorb
whatever territory you want to absorb
through movements on land. That's more
sustainable. Yeah.
Uh
okay. Gor of Rati says, "If Russia had
not developed nukes, would the US have
initially vasalized Russia? Are Russian
nukes the only reason why the world is
not a US vasal?" I think the only thing
that prevents nations from becoming
vasals of somebody else is the is the
final weapon. Um how many nations have
nukes? You have the US. You have Russia
which is which was formerly the USSR.
You have France. We have the UK. That's
four. Um
we have China obviously. That's that's
five. Then you have Israel, India,
Pakistan, North Korea. That's eight.
What am I missing? What am I missing?
I'm missing somebody. Uh list or List of
nuclear
countries.
North Korea. What? List of states with
nuclear weapons. What did I miss?
Um, North Korea, Israel, Pakistan,
India, China, France, UK. Yeah. Okay.
So, these are the nations. It's eight or
nine. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 nine. Nine
nations. All right. There we have it.
So, the US was the first nation to
acquire nuclear weapons. that the USSR
immediately as soon as possible acquired
nuclear weapons because it was very
important from for them to do that. Uh
then the Americans proliferated nuclear
weapons to several countries the UK and
France. The US proliferated nuclear
technology to the UK and France. Uh then
China developed nuclear weapons then
India and eventually other countries.
The Israel is also probably pro
benefited from American or or from
second order effects of US
proliferation. So you see France and the
UK did acquire nukes in the 1950s and
1960s but they are both American vasals.
So they developed nuclear weapons for
the benefit essentially of the US and
and and uh to serve as a bulv war
against the USSR because the US wanted
nuclear weapons in the continental
part of Western Europe and offshore part
of Western Europe as a bulv war against
the USSR. So that's why they
proliferated nuclear weapons to the UK
first and then then to France and they
were okay with Israel for some reason
acquiring nukes. Right? So
sometimes the overlord will proliferate
nuclear weapons to its vasals but do so
in a way that the nukes can never ever
be used against itself.
Uh and sometimes the only option a
nation has to avoid becoming a vasal is
to acquire nukes. That's what Russia,
the USSR did. That's what China did.
That's what India has done. Pakistan
most likely has American nuclear
warheads on loan or whatever and North
Korea has been possibly allowed by China
or possibly
maybe China proliferated nuclear nuclear
technology to North Korea. So it's
pretty complex and complicated that way.
Uh so the question you're asking is is
that is Russian nukes the only reason
why the US the whole world is not US? To
some extent there is some truth to that.
to some extent.
Uh Dir Kamat says why and how did the US
impose 15% tariffs on on Israel
of Israel? I have never claimed that the
US is a vasal of Israel. Uh let's see.
Uh US tariffs on Israel.
Let's see tariffs.
Uh
15% on Israel.
Let's see what it says.
um 2 percentage points lower than what
Trump ad
going to effect in 7 days. We'll use
tariffs as necessary. Um let's see
Trump 15% tariffs on Israeli goods.
The rate said of
the finance ministry responded that
Israel will Israel at the lower end
reflects positive dialogue.
So yeah, the US is indeed imposing
tariffs on Israel. And if you don't do
that, then it looks like you are the
vasal.
So it's okay.
How and why? Why and how? Well, how? We
know how it happened. The Trump
administration announced tariffs. So
it's like this. Look, if you are
imposing tariffs on the entire world,
but you exclude one nation, it looks
very bad. Yeah. So even if you have
special relationship with Israel,
uh it's it makes sense to impose tariffs
on Israel as well. I'm not sure if these
are blanket tariffs or whatever. I don't
think it'll hurt Israel too much. Israel
is a pretty prosperous nation, very high
GDP per capita and so on. It won't hurt
Israel too much. So I have never claimed
that the US is a Wasal of Israel by the
way. Okay. So
uh is it? Well, time will tell perhaps.
Who's who was? Who is whose Wasal? Time
will tell I suppose. Animesh Paul says
the US spends billions on wars yet its
health care remains broken and
expensive. Is this by design? Of course
it's by design.
Of course it's by design. Why not
prioritize affordable health care or and
or education? Do geopolitical interests
outweigh citizens well-being? The US is
a capitalist nation. Capitalism is
pretty rough on people who are not very
capable, very good at at earning money.
The US is is almost like a paradise for
people who are wealthy. If you are
wealthy in the US, which means if you
have a net worth in excess of at least
$5 million, it's it's it's a great
country. It's fantastic. It's paradise
for you. But if you are one of those
people who earns, let's say, $50,000 a
year, good god, it's hell.
Some people earn $30,000 a year. If you
are a low-skilled person, if you if you
don't have a great income, the US is
terrible for you. And that's the system.
That's the way the system is by design.
By design. Um the health the US can
certainly afford to give free healthcare
to everybody but they don't. Everything
has been
everything is an industry. Healthcare is
an industry. Agriculture is an industry.
Everything is an is an industry. And the
objective of the industry the objective
of the corporations is to maximize
profit at the expense of the people.
It's by design. It's by design. And this
has nothing to do with geopolitical
interests by the way. This is this is
the way the US has been for over a
century since the beginning of the 20th
century more or less roughly roughly
roughly roughly. It has nothing to do
with geopolitics. That is just the DNA
of the nation. That's how it is.
Okay. Herman Jot Singh says does anybody
going to re reconcile the fact that the
war started just because the US tried to
add Ukraine to NATO? Russia even said
that they will deescalate on refusal.
No, I think everybody knows that. But
the if you look at Western commentary,
they will blame Russia for starting the
war. If you see western analysts and
commentators and what they say on in
their in their pronouncements, in their
articles, in their social media posts,
they will say it's Russia's war on
Ukraine, Putin's war on Ukraine,
Russia's war economy. They try to place
the blame on Russia, but the fact is
undeniable
that it's it's the it's the West that
caused this war. They kept on marching
eastwards inexorably. They had given a
promise to the Russians that they would
not expand NATO further. But they kept
on expanding NATO further and further
eastwards
and Ukraine was the red line. Many
American analysts had warned that
Ukraine was a red line for Russia and
they had warned this more over a decade
before the actual war happened. More
than a decade before the war happened.
So the west western analysts will will
try and sidestep this fact. But the fact
is that the war started because of
American actions. First of all they
conducted a regime regime change
operation in Kiev in in Ukraine. In 2014
was it around 2014 the the Euromaidan
coup. I mean Victoria Newland was on was
was on the ground in in Kia when this
happened right and they ousted a
democratically constitutionally elected
government and replaced it with a puppet
regime of the west. It all started
there.
As a consequence, Russia quickly
reabsorbed Crimea and they they that
that is called an act of aggression by
the by the Americans by the West. That's
how it is. So it's very clear that the
war happened because of Western actions.
Russia was left with no choice but to
start the war but to conduct the
so-called special military operation.
WV says China or the US who is a bigger
long-term threat for India.
Well, look, neither are our friends and
both will continue to exist for a long
time. So, I think both
both see India as a problem. Both seek
to clip India's wings and cut India down
to size. Neither wants to see India
become prosperous and strong again in
the future and both are willing to use
Pakistan as as a stick to beat India
with. I think if you regard these two
nations as threats if you do and you
want to know which one is a longerterm
threat bigger longer long-term threat I
think both are equal in that sense both
are equal in that sense.
Mayang says this the Spanish the Ottoman
Empire the Roman Empire etc used tariffs
at the end at end tariffs etc that's
been used by in all economies
historically tariffs and there is
something called mercantalism and so on
so yeah you're right
um ICBM says you spoke about politicians
being lazy about energy security visa v
oil for example could the same thing be
said about nuclear energy given how
Well, France has done. Oh, absolutely.
And you can't blame the scientists and
engineers and technicians who work in
India's nuclear program for this. You
can't blame them. See, let's take the
example of France as the last see France
generates
about about 60 or 70% of France's
electrical energy comes from its nuclear
program, nuclear reactors. 60 to 70%.
You can look it up. You can look it up.
So France has been tremendously
successful at using nuclear power for
energy generation. The most successful
country in the world
and that saves France so much money. So
much money.
So India also has this longstanding
three-stage nuclear program that was
devised by Mr. Dr. Homie Baba back in
the 20th century middle 1960s or
something. And we have been very lax in
in implementing this. We have tremendous
thorium reserves in India. We have the
world's largest thorium reserves but we
have not taken the steps to
operationalize a full-fledged thorium
nuclear program, nuclear power program.
We're still dillydallying and taking
like little steps in the direction. So
yeah, you're absolutely right. We have
our our leaders
the leaders of the country have been
tremendously lazy
when it comes to uh taking the nuclear
program forward. By now we should have
been the world's biggest generator of
nuclear nuclear energy and electricity
via thorium but yeah there we are
unfortunate.
Sumit says is vokeness dying Sydney
Sweeney jeans commercial. This is not a
geopolitical topic sir. It's not right.
But yeah, it seems to be dying. All
right.
Uh Dhir Kamat says, "Why is Donald Trump
not releasing the Epstein fires? Is he
Is it likely that he too is a disgusting
predator?"
Well, I haven't seen those files, so I I
can should I speculate? I don't know.
So, let's consider the options, the
possibilities, the scenarios. One one
scenario is that yeah he may be on the
on the Epstein files. He may he may be
one of the people who is mentioned in
the files. That's one possibility.
Second possibility is that maybe he's
not mentioned in the Epson files but
very powerful very important people in
the US are mentioned in those files and
maybe they belong to both political
parties and it will be equally damaging
to both political parties. That's
another scenario. Number three scenario
is that maybe very powerful people,
world leaders from other countries are
mentioned in the Epstein files and if
you release the files then all of that
leverage that you have that the that the
US has or those those people it
evaporates because now they're outed and
there's no more blackmailing to be done
because now everyone knows. So there are
multiple scenarios that could explain
why Trump is not releasing the files. Uh
I remember his vice president Mr. Vance
was saying that the files need to be
released. Uh I remember Cash Patel the
FBI director in the past I think kind of
mentioned that those files need to be
released and so on. Trump also kind of
must have said in the past but now
they're all claiming that the files
don't exist at all. So so clearly there
is something at play over here.
All right. Wenutsai says what's the
origin of the Maui people? The
indigenous people of New Zealand. Their
facial features resemble Indians.
Were their origins connected to India in
any way? The Mai people,
they arrived in New Zealand less than a
thousand years ago. They are,
what's their ethnic group you're asking?
They are Polynesian people. The
Polynesian peoples. They are the
inhabitants of the South Pacific Ocean.
So, let's go to the maps. To the map.
Um we are familiar with this part of the
world and that part of the world but
there's this huge domain that's unchart
like not uncharted but it's like just
ocean the South Pacific and over here
you have all these little islands island
uh communities you have Fiji you have
Tonga the Cook Islands you have French
Polynesia you have Tahiti
um Tokilawu Kiribati Nauuru Toualu the
Solomon Islands New Calonia Vanuatu
uh the Marshall Islands, Micronesia, the
Northern Marana Islands, Palao, you have
Hawaii,
you have the Pit Karan Islands, you have
Hungaroa, which obviously no one lives
there anymore and so on. So the people
who live across all these islands, they
are the Polynesian people
and the people of New Zealand, the
Mauies are
one are ethnically part of that ethnic
group, the Polynesian people. And they
arrived in New Zealand less than a
thousand years ago.
Uh and there were the Mori also over
there. That's a whole different story
which we'll not delve into.
Um and even the people of Papua New
Guinea are part of the same overall
ethnic group. Uh is there a connection
with India? Not as far as I know. As far
as I know, there is no connection that I
know of with the people of India. There
could be but I don't know of any. All
right.
Arjun says should India have bought the
sub grippen with full technology
transfer as like they agree with
Thailand as the soul denied India
Rafal's source code
is there any guarantee they will give
you full technology transfer there's no
guarantee the grippen is is what Swedish
probably Swedish
they are a US asset you think they will
give us full technology transfer
eventually during the negotiations some
clauses will come up which will imply
that there will
full technology transfer won't happen.
Uh so no and again I don't know how good
or bad the aircraft is maybe it's a very
good aircraft whatever but how many
different kinds of aircraft do we want
to have in the country it's a absolute
nightmare for procuring spare parts for
getting servicing done for training
pilots for training technicians and
engineers it's a headache it's an
absolute nightmare when you have so many
different kinds of aircraft
I don't know what they have agreed with
Thailand Thailand if they are acquiring
the the the aircraft with full
technology transfer. Well, good luck to
them and congratulations. But I don't
think they will do that for India even
if they may have offered it to us. Uh
the denied Rafal source code I don't
know whatever that's how it goes. Look,
you have to you have to develop your own
aircraft which you control entirely. You
can buy certain aircraft as a stop gap
measure but you can't buy like hundreds
of different kinds of aircraft, a whole
zoo of different kinds of aircraft. It
becomes a nightmare. So I think it's a
good idea. Good thing that we did not
bought, we did not buy the Grippen.
I will not take political questions. I
will take geopolitics questions.
Right.
Rahul says, even though it's many
decades away, how would quantum
computing and quantum AI reshape
economy, warfare, humanity in general? I
am not sure if it's several decades
away. Quantum computing could become
more prevalent in in as much as a
decade's time. Every country is doing is
is has a quantum computing. Every major
country, every self-respecting country
is doing is taking quantum computing
research very seriously. Even India has
its own quantum computer now at least
one that I know of probably more. Uh and
there are issues in there are
difficulties in quantum computing and
all because of various factors. We we
will not go into the physics of that but
I think within a decade's time quantum
computing will be much more robust. I
think probably within two decades you
may have commercially available quantum
computers. Two decades at most in my
opinion in my assessment.
Um so once you have quantum computing
becoming significantly prevalent
it could reshape a lot of things. It
could make cryptography
well the present cryptographic templates
uh not templates techniques pretty
obsolete because cryptography is all
about encrypting information and quantum
computing will break that for sure.
warfare
warfare as well. Humanity in general I I
think look quantum computing gives you
more powerful computers. It allows
computers to do things that conventional
computers currently can't do. Very very
difficult problems can be solved easily
using quantum computers because of the
inherent nature of quantum
superpositions and entanglements and all
that. So uh so essentially what it means
forget about the the the scientific
terms and all that technical terms
quantum computers when they arrive will
be way more powerful than regular
computers for a specific number of
tasks. So that will allow us to do
better jobs at drug discovery and
molecular u molecule discovery probably
solving diseases
curing diseases like cancer and so on.
um warfare. Warfare obviously encryption
will become more difficult. Uh
entanglement. So
yeah, it it will it will give you radars
that can break stealth technology that
can detect stealth aircraft and so much
more. So overall it's it just means that
you have computers that are super
powerful and which can do things that
you can't currently do with normal
computers. And when you take quantum
computing and merge it with AI, it will
be a whole different dimension. So yeah,
obviously it's going to be very
powerful. It's going to be
transformative for the world as we know
it. You know, I think overall it's
humanity is going to be it's going to be
a whole different ride for humanity
going forward and it's starting right
now actually.
Um Arun says anyway I can think of
Pakistan and US finding oil is by
occupying international waters in
Arabian Sea. Is it possible? Am I
overthinking? Do we have any known major
oil discoveries in the so-called Arabian
Sea, the western Indian Ocean? I am not
aware of any.
If there is something, well, good for
them. Uh they can't occupy international
waters. International waters, anybody
can occupy that way. Uh they can see
Pakistan if it wants to uh dig for oil
and extract oil, it can only do that in
its territorial waters or within its
exclusive economic zone, not beyond
that. If the US uh helps Pakistan in
doing something like that, you're
essentially breaking international law,
right? That's not good. Of course, it's
possible because the US can do anything
it's want it it wants. It's the most
powerful country in the world. It's
certainly possible. So, I would not say
you are overthinking. It's definitely
within the realm of possibility.
We'll see. Yeah.
Um Aditya Adita Bandari says, "Did Trump
fail in destroying the the drug
cartels?" Look these drug cartels.
Where do they exist? Some exist in
Mexico. Some exist in Colombia. The
Colombian cartels are the classic famous
ones, infamous ones, right? The
notorious ones. The Kali cartel, the
Sinaloa cartel, the Bedin cartel.
Cartel. Uh Don Pablo Escobar was the
boss of the Medí cartel and so on. The
question you to ask yourselves is this.
These cartels that produce drugs, who is
the customer? Who's the consumer? What
is the market, the target market? It's
the US.
It's the US. Now, you also have to ask
yourself yourselves. Why is it so easy
to acquire drugs in the US? Drugs are
available everywhere in the US.
Everybody drug does drugs at some point
in their life. That's how the US is. If
drugs are illegal, why are they so easy
to obtain? Isn't the US the greatest
nation in law enforcement? So why are
they allowing allowing drugs to be so
easy to procure?
It's for some reason they want their
people to be hooked to drugs it looks
like. So why would they then then
destroy the cartels? They don't they
will not destroy the cartels. Yeah.
Okay. Godliness says in the last 13
years India has signed three important
strategic pacts with the US. Limoa,
Gasonia, Kasa. Will it cost us in the
future? Also some words on US defense
policy for the Indian Ocean.
We have indeed signed these pacts and
these pacts they allow some kind of U US
penetration of U Indian defense systems
to a certain extent certain extent not
full but to a certain extent so we have
indeed signed these packs because we
were trusting of the US will it cost us
in the future look all we have to do is
to walk away from the pacts
it's not impossible
hasn't the US walked away from the JCPOA
with Iran, the joint comprehensive P
plan of action, the Iran nuclear deal,
the US walked away un unilaterally from
that. Uh the Chinese walked away unil
unilaterally from their deal with the UK
visa v Hong Kong one nation two systems.
The Chinese walked away unilaterally.
India walked away un unilaterally from
the Indust treaty. Similarly, if you
have signed a pact with somebody, you
can walk away from it. Of course, the US
will not be pleased with such an action,
but we can walk away if it if it is
potentially going to be bad for our
national interest. Yeah. Uh it may cost
us something. The US may take actions
that are bad for us. They may throw more
tantrums and so on. That that could
happen for sure. But it is what it is.
So if it is in the national interest to
walk away from the pact, we can do it.
Um for that we may have to stop using
the US equipment we have bought. Of
course, it the walking away from the
pacts may make that equipment unusable
for us,
but it is what it is. Maybe it's a price
we may have to pay. Uh some words on US
defense policy for the Indian Ocean.
Um the US has assets in the Indian Ocean
region. If you look at the map,
um see if you look at the Indian Ocean,
the major power is obviously India. Uh
we also have France which is a
significant power in in India. Uh the
French have uh certain assets in the in
Indian in an ocean region like Runo and
uh certain other islands. Where are
those islands? French southern antarctic
lands and so on. Uh Alfred I'm not sure
if it's French or not. Is it French?
Yeah, I think it's French.
Iloilosong which means the island of the
pigs island with pigs or whatever and so
so the French have some assets in the
Indian Ocean region and that's why they
have a presence here and France and
India are pretty pretty are essentially
co cooperating when it comes to Indian
Ocean security when it comes to the US
presence in the Indian Ocean region they
have lots of air bases and naval bases
in the Gulf region they have something
in Djibouti They obviously have a power
projection center in uh south of the
Maldives which is the which is Diego
Garcia from which they can launch uh
strategic bombers to bomb any country
they want in the region and so on and
they obviously have Australia which is a
US well US asset. So they
so the Indian Ocean region for the US is
not that important because they don't
have any major threats or enemies in the
region.
uh as India grows and becomes more
powerful, they may choose to focus more
on the Indian Ocean region in the
future. We'll see about that. Okay.
Rahul says, "How could techno capitalism
and geopolitics evolve in the coming
years? Can China catch up with a silicon
and high NA alternative ASML
competitor?
Can China catch up?" um
how will all of this evolve? Look,
technology is an integral component of
geopolitics. The nations that rule the
world are generally the nations that are
the most technologically advanced.
That's that's something you have seen
throughout history, right? And that's
why what you will see is that the
current geopolitical race in the world
the the the competition that we are
seeing the geopolitical competition
between the US and China is also a
technological competition. It's a
technological arms race that we are
seeing right now. And it is the
technological arms race that is driving
the geopolitical race and the the the
trade and tariffs race also that that
that war that's happening right now that
also there's a significant technological
undercurrent to everything. Technology
to some extent is a is a driver of
what's happening. So why has the US now
decided to to go allin against China? It
all started with Trump around 2019 or so
when he imposed certain restrictions on
exports American exports to China the
chips act or whatever it was Biden
continued that so why did they choose to
do this around 2019 until that time the
US was the biggest trade partner of
China right but around 2019 they started
imposing these restrictions on China
because they realized that China is
beginning to catch up with the US
technologically in a very dangerous way
so that's why this is going on now the
Chinese They are now facing all these,
you could almost call them sanctions,
right? Sanctions, technological
sanctions and and technology denial from
the US. Nvidia is not allowed to sell
certain chips to China and so on. So the
Chinese are trying to create their own
technology, their own ASML alternative.
They're trying to create their own photo
lithographic technology that will allow
them, enable them to uh manufacture
their own high-end chips, GPUs and
whatnot. they are trying to do that and
they are not doing a bad job of it.
Okay. So it's quite likely see the
Chinese what they've done is they
invested trillions of dollars in two
things since the 1990s.
They invested trillions of dollars very
systematically on two things. First
their education system and second their
technological ecosystem. And the
education system is what feeds the
technological ecosystem because they
focus their education system on science
and technology. They they made it a
point to ensure that their universities
become some of the best universities in
the world. Research-driven driven
universities. They they hunted down and
attract the and and attracted the best
talent teaching talent to China to
China's universities. They reformed the
education system thoroughly. So now the
education system produces highquality
engineers and techn technicians and
scientists and those then
go and fit into the technological
ecosystem that China has. So they
identified the the core technology the
critical technologies that China needs
to master around 2000 around the year
2000 and they brought in foreign experts
to help them. So, it's been a very
systematic step-by-step process that
they've taken
and they've invested trillions of
dollars worth of wealth into that and
that's why they're in a position where
they can actually compete with the US.
So, it's a it's a technological arms
race that's going to be neck and neck
essentially over the coming years. The
advantage the US has is that they have
got a big head start. They've got the
Silicon Valley thing and all the Chinese
are now developing their own, you know,
parallel systems. their competitors and
they're doing a very good job. The real
advantage of the US is its global power
projection capabilities and China is
betting that their technological advance
advances will help them overcome the US
advantages and that's what's going on.
So it's going to be a neck andneck race
in the coming years.
Arun says Australia's first rocket
launch failed. I was surprised that that
they could not do it and the western
media sphere looks down upon India
whenever we launch something. Well,
that's how it goes. Like I said, the
west the west is deeply unhappy that
India even exists. They would have
wanted us to be to have been totally
destroyed by the British during the two
and a half centuries of occupation. And
the fact that we are still polytheists
majorly is is a huge irritant for the
west. So if something goes wrong in
India, they will highlight highlight it
for weeks. If something happens,
something goes wrong in a western
nation, well, they just keep quiet about
that. That's how it goes.
Anonymous scientist says, what should
India do if China invades Taiwan?
First of all, India should stay out of
the matter, but if required, India
should take steps to secure nations in
our periphery. Secure I am I don't mean
invade secure essentially Nepal, Bhutan,
Sri Lanka etc.
Whatever steps need to be taken.
Koshel says how does the long-term
future 100 years for India look like?
I'm both afraid and hopeful at the same
time. What's your 100year outlook for
India?
Look, if I am to be optimistic, in a 100
years you will have Indian citizens
living on various cities in Mars on
Mars. In a 100 years, if I am to be
optimistic, India will be the major
power in the world, the uh most advanced
technological power and obviously
economic and geopolitical power. If
Indians are living on Mars, it means
that we have essentially reached the
stars,
the step stepping stone to the stars.
That is if everything goes well. for
that to happen the next 20 years is the
most crucial right uh the worst thing
that you can imagine is that India gets
balconized and it's over for India uh
that's also a possibility but I am by
nature an optimistic person so I think I
am confident I'm optimistic that India
will be able to overcome all the
challenges and difficulties India will
be able to withstand everything that the
west and the other in the rest of the
world throws at us over the next 20
India will be able to overcome all of
that. India will be able to grow and
rise again. India will be able to return
to its indigenous cultural and
civilizational roots and throw away the
the vestigages of colonialism that we
are laboring under right now. And I'm
optimistic that great leaders will
emerge in India. And I think in a 100
years Indians will be living in cities
on Mars and India will have conquered
space. And India will be the most
advanced
and prosperous nation civilization
on the planet.
MK says, "Could Kamala have been better
for India?" Well,
maybe if you look at the way things are
going, maybe you could say Biden and
Kamala would have been better for India.
Okay.
A rational reporter says if the
parliament makes a law giving the prime
minister option to use military like we
did in Sri Lanka and Maldives to stop a
coup in our neighborhood if the country
requests, could that help prevent future
Bangladesh like situations? The the
parliament of India does not need to
enact a law giving prime the prime
minister that option. The prime minister
already has the option. The prime
minister of India
must do whatever it takes to safeguard
and and promote India's interests
wherever required. I don't think
parliament needs to enact a law for for
for that to happen. Yeah. Uh so if
there's a coup in the neighborhood
that's going going to happen or about to
happen or happening that will be bad for
India. I think the the prime minister of
India has the option to intervene if
required
and that obviously could help us prevent
future Bangladesh like situations.
Parthan says which countries are likely
to succeed at quantum uh computing?
Definitely the US, definitely China,
India also could be on the way. Uh
European nations like France possibly
could do that. Russia could possibly do
that. Who else can I see? maybe Israel,
maybe Israel,
Japan, obviously Japan, maybe even South
Korea. So all the nations that are
technologically advanced have have high
quality
um technological ecosystems etc will do
that. I think India also will do pretty
well. We are on the way to that. Yeah.
Okay. Wamshi Khal says, "What GDP can we
unilaterally take action at? 10, 15 or
20?
Right now we we're closing in on 5
trillion. Right now we can't
unilaterally take action like what the
US can do. Uh China is at $18 trillion.
Even China today cannot unilaterally
take action like invading Taiwan. So I
think we will have to b our time maybe
until 20.
Okay let's say until 20. Give it 20
years. Work as hard as possible. All of
us in 20 years if we are at $20 trillion
maybe we will be able to take unilateral
action. Yes.
Okay. Pratam Sony says in the Galwan
clash what Modi government act action
was different from past governments what
changed China POV versus India what led
to five years standoff and some tips to
raise what? Ask one question.
Excuse me. Let's take one question at a
time.
Galwan clash the first armed clash
between the two nations for I don't know
since the 1980s or something maybe even
before that the first time bullets were
fired in multiple decades the first
deaths for for since I think I think the
1960s death of soldiers on both sides
um so why did the cash happen it's
because the Chinese were very very
getting very upset and and anxious ious
about the infrastructure development on
the Indian side of the line of actual
control. For decades, Indian governments
had not bothered to develop any
infrastructure on the Indian side. So
what action did the Modi government take
first of all that caused this from
China's perspective? From China's side,
it is the Modi government doubling down
on creating as much infrastructure as
possible as rapidly as possible. You go
to the border regions, you will see bro
BR border roads organization working day
and night day and night. Whatever
weather it is, whether it is raining,
whether it is snowing, whether there are
there's a hail storm, they are always
working. We are building infrastructure
as fast as is humanly possible. We're
building roads, we are building whatever
is required. And the Chinese were very
upset about this and they were trying to
push and that's why the clash happened.
And after the clash happened the
government of India and the Modi
government like you said did not back
down. We had a standoff with China for
se for for several years face to face.
In the past the Indian government would
have backed down from that. So a lot
changed a lot has changed now. This is a
different India obviously right.
Udai Kumar says can the US freeze
India's forex reserves like Russia? Do
we have assets that the are based in the
US? If we have assets that are based in
the US the US can obviously freeze
those. Yeah. So it's best not to do
that. Arun says as a backpacker I have
noticed western tourists come to India
to see the spiritual side of India. They
want to do yoga etc. Eastern tourists
like to experience food of various
regions. We should be using food
software the way we use yoga. I I could
not agree agree more with you. I
completely agree with you. We have such
an tremendous diversity of cuisines in
this country in India. Every state has
multiple cuisines in the various local
regions. Every 50 kmters there's a new
cuisine. We should start culinary
schools in each state.
Every state should have multiple
culinary institutes
where you are taught cuisine and it's
presented and and served at the highest
standards.
Why can't we do that? We have the best
cuisines in the world but we don't serve
them properly. We don't showcase them
properly. It's all about presentation.
It's all about style. It's all about the
way you put it across.
India has the potential to be the
world's premier tourism destination to
be a tourism superpower.
It's a lowhanging fruit. We are doing
nothing about it. It's such a shame. So
Arun, I I completely agree with you.
Completely.
Sedant VMA says, "Could Iranian
Azarbaijan and Kuzastan break away from
Iran due to separatists, separatist
movements? How come half of Iranians
identify as non-Persian like Gilakis,
Azaris, Arabs, etc.?" Because they are
not Persian.
Why do half of Iranians identify as
non-Persian? Because ethnically they are
not Persian. Ethnically they are Azaris.
Ethnically they're Arabs. Ethnically
they are Baluchi. Ethnically they're
whatever else. How did that happen?
Well, Iran like India was for quite some
time under Turk occupation.
Let's say part of the Quarasma Empire.
Then the Quarasma Empire was destroyed
by Shir Chingishan. Then you had other
Turk Turk empires. That evil
what's the what's the monster? Let's
call it call him monster. That evil
monster Nad Sha who sacked Delhi and and
and
genocided the people of Delhi. He was a
Turk. He was not Persian. So when the
the Turks were ruling Persia, they
brought in lots of people from other
parts of their empire out non-Persian
parts of the empire and had them settled
in Persia. If you look at the people of
Iran today, many of them actually look
white. There are people with blonde
hair, people with blue eyes or green
eyes or whatever. There are many people
in Iran who look almost European,
right? Those are the non-persian people.
those are the non-persian people. Um so
that's it's the Turk rulers of Iran who
brought in people from other parts of
the world from other parts of Eurasia,
people from the Caucasus region, people
from Turk parts of their empires and so
on. And that's why today you have the
situation where half of Iranians they
are of other ethnicities. Now Iranian,
Azarbaijan, Kazan etc break away from
Iran due to separate separatist
movements. Well, if the government of
Iran becomes weak then anything can
happen. So the the trick is do not
become weak.
Okay.
Okay. We have crossed two hours. Let's
take a couple of questions. Sparti says,
"Do you think importing minerals from
other countries for use now and
preserving our own resources until
others run out could be considered a
strategic approach?" It's not a bad
approach. If we have our own resources,
if we have our own reserves of strategic
minerals and what not and we don't want
to use them up because maybe they're
limited, then it makes sense to import
from other countries and import as long
as as it's possible, right? Yeah, it
makes sense. It's it's a it's a good
it's a prudent approach to have. I would
agree with that. Yes. Um,
what else do we have? Let's let me take
a couple of questions.
Let me take a couple of questions.
Sur says your subscriber count is not
crossing 949K. We will discuss that at
at a
next week. Yeah, you're right. You're
right.
Okay, let's take maybe this is the final
question. All right, let's take this as
the final question.
Uh Dhir says, you have often stated that
India does not seek to be a hedgeim.
Don't you think that it's necessary to
be a hedgeman for the superpower to
remain one? Well, if you are in the
position where you are a superpower, it
means that you have reached there. What
what is the definition of superpower?
Once again, going back to first
principles, first of all, let's define
what superpower means. My definition,
yours may differ, but my definition of
superpower is that a superpower is a
nation that can intervene militarily
anywhere in the world at 60 minutes
notice. It means that it has global
power position capabilities. It means
that it has a global military footprint.
It means that it has military bases all
across the world. That is pure hegemonic
behavior. So the US is a superpower and
to remain a superpower the US needs to
be a hgemon and it needs to continue to
be a hgemon. Now if India aspires to be
a superpower
in that case we essentially it means
that we aspire to replace and displace
the US as the superpower and become the
global hedgeim
we it's not part of our culture it's not
something we've ever been like but if we
want to be a superpower it means we have
to do that for that you will have to be
a hammen no question about it right do
we want to be that do do that do we want
to have global power production
capability do we want to have military
bases on other pe other nations
territory all across the world. I would
I would like to ask you all is that what
you uh is that what you want
India to do. So I think it it depends.
See we are a very democratic nation. I
think the people have to decide what
kind of nation we want to become and if
it's if if that's what you all want then
that's the kind of nation India should
aspire to be but for that you have to
take appropriate action.
Right. Right. Okay. Okay, so we are at
the end of today's live stream. Thank
you so much. It was great fun. It was
great fun. I really enjoyed all the
questions. A very diverse set of
questions within the theme of
geopolitics and I look forward to doing
the same thing next week once again. So
until next week and we will discuss some
other things next week. Next week is
going to be a little different. So thank
you so much. Take care. Good day. Good
night and I will see you in the next
live stream. Take care. Thank